<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-22T21:02:02+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/datasophy/</id><title type="html">A Philosopher’s Guide to Data Science</title><subtitle>Discussions around data science, GDPR, law, philosophy, data ethics, big data, and the occasional little data tutorial</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How Schrems led to the Invalidation of Safe Harbor in 2015</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/summary-schrems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Schrems led to the Invalidation of Safe Harbor in 2015" /><published>2018-06-22T17:58:36+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T17:58:36+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/summary-schrems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/summary-schrems.html">&lt;p&gt;The Schrems case was the culmination of several other landmark “digital rights” cases that eventually led to the invalidation of Safe Harbor. In 2013, the Austrian citizen Max Schrems made a complaint to the Irish Data Protection Commissioner in which it was claimed that Facebook-Ireland’s transfer of EU citizens’ personal data to the US violated EU law. At the time, these kinds of transfers were legally valid under the Safe Harbor agreement. Essentially, the argument made by Schrems was that in light of Edward Snowden’s leaking of classified US government surveillance programs, “there was no meaningful protection in US law or practice” for personal data transferred to the US because US law enforcement could obtain access to personal data without a court order (ibid.). Initially, Schrems’ complaint was dismissed and thrown out by the Irish DPA because Schrems could not demonstrate that his personal data were actually affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, just one year later, the Irish High Court ruled differently and concluded that Schrems did in fact have legal standing under EU law, due primarily to the Digital Rights Ireland holding which stated that it did not matter if the complainant had been personally affected in order to show that his right to respect for private life (Articles 7 &amp;amp; 8 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights) had been infringed (ibid.). The court also expressed concerns about US law enforcement surveillance and the lack of personal data protections in US law. In particular, the court noted that EU data subjects had no effective means of judicial review under Safe Harbor for privacy complaints (ibid.). Ultimately, the court found that the “adequacy” of the protection given to personal data in the Safe Harbor agreement was not enough and declared it invalid in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Schrems case was the culmination of several other landmark “digital rights” cases that eventually led to the invalidation of Safe Harbor. In 2013, the Austrian citizen Max Schrems made a complaint to the Irish Data Protection Commissioner in which it was claimed that Facebook-Ireland’s transfer of EU citizens’ personal data to the US violated EU law. At the time, these kinds of transfers were legally valid under the Safe Harbor agreement. Essentially, the argument made by Schrems was that in light of Edward Snowden’s leaking of classified US government surveillance programs, “there was no meaningful protection in US law or practice” for personal data transferred to the US because US law enforcement could obtain access to personal data without a court order (ibid.). Initially, Schrems’ complaint was dismissed and thrown out by the Irish DPA because Schrems could not demonstrate that his personal data were actually affected.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are Binding Corporate Rules and How are They Useful?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/bcrs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are Binding Corporate Rules and How are They Useful?" /><published>2018-06-22T17:58:36+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T17:58:36+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/bcrs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/bcrs.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-bcrs&quot;&gt;What are BCRs?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BCRs can be summarized as a voluntary “set of binding rules that can be put in place to allow multinational groups to transfer personal data from the European Economic Area (EEA) to affiliates outside the EEA in compliance with national laws implementing the EU Directive” (Allen &amp;amp; Overy 2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-do-they-entail&quot;&gt;What do they entail?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 47 (2)(a-n) of the GDPR spells out the specific requirements for a corporation’s binding corporate rules: at the very least they must include complaint procedures, a statement of the privacy principles they follow, auditing and employee training mechanisms, the acceptance of liability for any rule breaches, and an explanation of how data subjects can access the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whom-are-the-binding-on&quot;&gt;Whom are the binding on?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BCRs are legally binding on the corporation, the employees of the corporation, data subjects–through the notion of third party beneficiary rights–and any independent contractors the corporation deals with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;can-i-do-whatever-i-want-if-i-have-a-bcr&quot;&gt;Can I do whatever I want if I have a BCR?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that BCRs do not cover international data transfers to firms that are not subsidiaries or contractors, unlike other data transfer agreements such as the APEC Privacy Framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;do-bcrs-exist-for-third-party-processors-as-well&quot;&gt;Do BCRs exist for third-party processors as well?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, BCRs can also cover third party processors that process personal data on behalf of the data controllers, which allows them to cover the use of cloud transfers across borders (Reding 2011). Such agreements would typically be included in the Service Level Agreement (SLA) between the controller and processor (Allen &amp;amp; Overy 2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it should be emphasized that BCRs do not allow firms carte blanche to collect and process personal data; the existence of BCRs merely allows a corporation to transfer personal data within the corporate network (and to its data processors), to countries in which there may not be adequate personal data protection laws.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What are BCRs?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Common GDPR Misconceptions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/three-common.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Common GDPR Misconceptions" /><published>2018-06-22T17:57:36+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T17:57:36+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/three-common</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/three-common.html">&lt;h1&gt;“The GDPR is totally new.”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually it borrows most of its language from the 1995 Directive, with a few small but important additions and updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;“Only firms that process EU citizens’ data will be affected.”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, your data subjects don’t need to be EU citizens under GDPR to be protected. Anyone residing (even American tourists) in the EU . Or if you offer product or service in EU. Or you collect personal data from data subjects in the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;“GDPR will destroy my business. I have to get explicit consent now to process personal data.”&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope! Consent is just one of several grounds of processing. Actually, since the requirements of explicit consent are so strict, it might be better to use other means. Gradually work your way down from consent to legit interest to statistical research&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“The GDPR is totally new.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The FTC’s Role in Data Protection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/ftc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The FTC's Role in Data Protection" /><published>2018-06-22T17:57:36+08:00</published><updated>2018-06-22T17:57:36+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/ftc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/datasophy/2018/06/22/ftc.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;personal-data-regulation-in-the-usa-the-ftcs-role&quot;&gt;Personal Data Regulation in the USA: The FTC’s Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The de facto regulation of companies that collect and analyze data in the USA mainly falls under the purview of the Federal Trade Commission in its role as enforcer of the Federal Trade Commission Act of 1914. Under the Act, the FTC was given powers to protect consumers and business against “unfair or deceptive practices in commerce.” Although the FTC has no direct punitive powers, it reserves the right to seek enforcement of the FTC Act by district courts and thereby obtain civil penalties (i.e., fines) for violations that “cause or [are] likely to cause substantial injury to consumers which is not reasonably avoidable by consumers themselves and not outweighed by countervailing benefits to consumers or to competition”. The FTC will first make a determination whether it has “sufficient reason to believe” a firm is acting unfairly or deceptively towards consumers and then, with the assistance of a district court, either file a Civil Investigative Complaint (CID) or a subpoena demanding information from the company regarding the FTC’s inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-weakness-of-the-ftc&quot;&gt;The Weakness of the FTC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the EU’s GDPR, the FTC’s regulatory influence and ability to economically disincentivize bad actors is relatively weak. In 2003, for instance, the major food companies Hershey’s and Mrs. Fields were found to violate the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA) by obtaining children’s personal information without first requiring parental consent. The companies were fined $85,000 and $100,000, respectively. At that time, these penalties were the largest COPPA civil penalties ever recorded by the FTC. Considering that Hershey’s 2003 sales revenues were $4.17B, this was a a mere drop in the bucket. More recently in 2016, the FTC targeted the Taiwanese company ASUS when it claimed that ASUS used deceptive advertising to describe its routers as safe to hacking, when in fact nearly 13,000 of them had been exploited by hackers. ASUS was forced to pay only $16,000 per violation  and submit to independent security audits every two years for the next 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ftc-is-all-about-being-technology-neutral&quot;&gt;The FTC is all about being “technology neutral”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, the FTC’s general approach to personal data regulation is light-touch and focuses on the key ideas of legal certainty, economic incentive, and innovation. The FTC believes industry-self regulation is a laudable goal, but has largely failed in the area of internet technology. Instead, federal regulation is needed, but only at a base level that is “technology neutral” and leaves considerable room for individual industries and firms to best decide on how exactly to comply. Part of the reason in choosing to support basic regulation is that it will provide firms with the “certainty they need to understand their obligations;” additionally, the threat of punishment gives some incentive to meet those legal obligations. And finally, base regulation will give consumers confidence that businesses must respect their privacy, which will spur consumer activity.  In short, the FTC rejects prescriptive regulation and can be viewed as a currently “default hybrid” system of governance with aspirations towards a more robust “baseline hybrid” system. Time will tell whether the FTC’s exhortations will influence Congress enough to pass a baseline federal law regarding personal data protection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Personal Data Regulation in the USA: The FTC’s Role The de facto regulation of companies that collect and analyze data in the USA mainly falls under the purview of the Federal Trade Commission in its role as enforcer of the Federal Trade Commission Act of 1914. Under the Act, the FTC was given powers to protect consumers and business against “unfair or deceptive practices in commerce.” Although the FTC has no direct punitive powers, it reserves the right to seek enforcement of the FTC Act by district courts and thereby obtain civil penalties (i.e., fines) for violations that “cause or [are] likely to cause substantial injury to consumers which is not reasonably avoidable by consumers themselves and not outweighed by countervailing benefits to consumers or to competition”. The FTC will first make a determination whether it has “sufficient reason to believe” a firm is acting unfairly or deceptively towards consumers and then, with the assistance of a district court, either file a Civil Investigative Complaint (CID) or a subpoena demanding information from the company regarding the FTC’s inquiry.</summary></entry></feed>